<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Devendra Vyas's Blog</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2020-05-28T22:32:13+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Devendra Vyas</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Generative vs Discriminative Model</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/23/generative-vs-discriminative-model/"/>
   <updated>2020-05-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/23/generative-vs-discriminative-model</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Excerpts from my quarantine</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/excerpts-from-my-quarantine/"/>
   <updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/excerpts-from-my-quarantine</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was diagnosed with a comparatively rarer strain of a bacterial infection &amp;amp; quarantined for around 4 months from Oct-2017 to Feb-2018. During that time I realized that more than anything else it was a test of my mental strength than vigor. Seeing the current situation most of the world is on self-quarantine at home while many tested positive for COVID-19 are in healthcare facilities. When I was in the hospital, I was desperately searching for blogs/videos/books to give me some hope so, this time I’m making an attempt to hopefully be a part of someone’s search result looking for the same hope I once sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to bore you but to give you a brief context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16 October 2017, somewhere around 16:30 CET, I’ve issues in just maintaining a straight posture on a chair. Have you ever seen those tall buildings falling onto itself, well I felt kind of like that in my spine. I left work, went home and tried to sleep. It got worse with every passing minute. I went to the hospital, instantly admitted for the night to run some tests and then sent home for 2–3 days. My situation really didn’t improve and I was hoping tests would reveal the issue. To my dismay, they didn’t! I was admitted again, this time for a week and then was again told to go home for a weekend and return on Monday. Well, this time when I returned, little did I know that I would be moving in with them(CHU Poitiers, France) for the foreseeable future. Here I was, in a country that was still new to me. I had severely limited (read non-existent) language skills, a few friends for support but just for the initial few days (After the first few weeks they couldn’t even if they wanted to). No possibility of a family member to be around for boosting morale. Worst of all the doctors had the same statements which my friends have been telling me since ages “There’s something wrong with you but we don’t know what!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/public/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png&quot; alt=&quot;A doodle I made on the letter for my doctors once I was released as a gesture of gratitude&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now that you know some background, I’ll try to jot down a few of my experiences from that time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First 2 weeks: Hope and Dealing with delusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In the first 2 weeks of my quarantine, my spirits were quite high. I was cracking jokes with the doctors, (somehow) enjoying the bland hospital meals, talking with my family with a smile. All of this, because in my head the narrative was that I’ll be out in a matter of days. They were performing so many tests on me. Maybe it’s the French way of giving someone medical tourism. Either that or some poor chap’s Ph.D. thesis was on the line and it was dependent on my test results… Either way, I was more curious than afraid of knowing what I have!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unknown gets scary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Post the first 2–3 weeks, I remember it was about mid of November &amp;amp; now I’m really expecting some solid answers from my doctors but instead I got to learn 2 new sentences in French “Je ne sais pas, Monsieur ” (I don’t know!), something that my doctors would constantly say and my response to it “Alors, Laissez moi sortir!” (Then, Let me out!). Never said in an aggressive way but rather as a request. Staying locked in a room with no idea when the situations would change for the better could get scary but if there’s one thing that I learned was to accept the “new normal” as quickly as you can, which brings me to my next point :&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepting the new normal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Two weeks after that last incident I was told that now I’d be moved to a negative air-pressure room (Fancy word for a room with an exhaust). I won’t lie the very construction of that entrance with its two air-gaped doors, scared the shit out of me for a good day or two BUT then I said to myself “This has better facilities than my shared apartment” and with that one statement echoing in my head I just somehow felt better :) Sometimes, it’s just about the narrative you say to yourself that has the power to alter the perception of reality!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perception of time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I’ll now make an attempt at explaining something that I don’t have a full grasp of and I hope no one has to go through this experience. When you are in quarantine or even a closed facility with severely limited interaction and no information on how long it would last, your semantic understanding of time changes. It’s quite organic since for many it could be the first time in their lives that they get to observe an entire span of a day and more importantly their own thoughts for an extended period of time. In our normal life, some sort of routine helps us remain sane. But in quarantine, that thing is suddenly missing!
 So, a simple solution is to try &amp;amp; create a routine out of the limited set of activities you can do and stick to it. What it would do is give your brain a thing to think of next throughout the day. At times when you cannot do anything, write your thoughts, it doesn’t need to be a linear string of scenes, you don’t have to give it Good or Bad labels, it doesn’t even need to make any sense but you just need to create a channel for it come under the analysis of your conscious mind. If you can’t write, sit and try to observe your thoughts whenever it gets over-whelming; don’t fight them, don’t suppress them. Just try to be an observer. Overwhelming feelings and/or emotions disappear really soon once they come under conscious analysis. There have been times when I said it aloud to myself “I feel really bad at this moment and I’m possibly going to cry for no reason now!” and then minutes later it changed to “Well, they(Hospital staff) will definitely be irritated by me at some point and let me go”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annoyingly happy patient&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;What would follow in days to come is that I would greet every doctor, resident doctors, and nurses with a smile and a sentence that used to surprise them a bit sometime, “ Bonjour/Bonsoir! ça va?” (Good morning/evening, How are you?). The surprise was because they thought they were supposed to ask that. Whenever a nurse would politely ask me is there anything you need, I would simply reply “Pizza aux champignons et oignons s’il vous plait!” (Pizza with mushrooms and onions please!). I know it was stupid, unreasonable BUT if it doesn’t hurt anyone and helps you remain sane, why not!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My support system&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I had a few friends that came every now and then as they could and stayed with me for 30–60 min as anything more than that wasn’t really allowed. I had massive emotional support from my family back in India. Every single day my parents would call me twice, my aunts &amp;amp; my cousins would call me almost as regularly. We sometimes played online games together like Ludo. All of this did act as a good diversion from my reality.
 If you’re in quarantined, call your friends, family, anyone you like to talk to; it does help! If you’re in self-quarantine or social-distancing, then talking to another person in the same conditions shouldn’t be hard. Most people would very much welcome that thought; it’s just gathering the courage to take that first step!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t really want to turn this experience sharing into preaching but just to highlight the key takeaway points&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things are gonna get worse before they get worst but always for the better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance of the moment of the truth is a simple yet powerful tool (I totally understand you that it might not be so easy to adopt though)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It might feel like a slightly unusual change in your lifestyle both in a spatial and temporal manner but the discomfort will fade over time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your version of reality could be a conscious choice of self-narrative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if it looks awful, even if the unknown bothers you, even if being lonely isn’t necessarily your cup of tea just keep saying to yourself “This too shall pass”. This works irrespective of your mood!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please share it if you liked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Being Lonely Or Being Alone</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/16/being-lonely-or-being-alone/"/>
   <updated>2018-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/16/being-lonely-or-being-alone</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;!-- ---
layout: post
title: Being lonely or being alone?
comments: true
--- --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are asked for absolutely no reason “Hey! How are you? “ , doesn’t matter you know me or not, doesn’t matter you’re taking a stroll or in a hurry, doesn’t matter you are in a good mood or not, your instinct will throw the very first answer as “I’m fine” Or “I’m good” Or “I’m OK!” (Pick your poison).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be an indication to a problem. A symptom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is this popular video on YouTube titled Simon Sinek on Millennial and Internet Addiction. If you can spare 20 minutes, please go and watch it before reading further. If you don’t want to watch, here are the key points he mentions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Millennials(People born in 90s) could be characterized as the people grown under the influence of these 4 key factors:

1. Failed parenting strategies (Been told they can get anything they want, just because they want it. They can be anything!)

Effect: An entire generation that is growing up on failed self-esteem of previous generation

2.Internet (A life of filters, good at showing people that life is amazing even when one is depressed)

Effect: A dopamine driven lifestyle

3. Sense of Impatience (Grown in an age of instant gratification)

Effect: Failure to accept that it doesn’t work for job satisfaction and relationships

4. Environment ( Corporate preference for short term gain than long term life of young minds)

Effect: They end up thinking they lack the skill-set to develop in this environment
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now some of you might relate to all of what he said. Some will find a part of it relevant . But probably no one would discard everything being mentioned. The moment you acknowledge a coherence with any one of those issues, you should start to realize there IS some problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduating in mid-2016, I had 6 long months of doing substantially N.O.T.H.I.N.G. Travel ideas went to ashes because Gareebi (Poverty/Lack-of-Money). Having said that, there are 2 journeys every human must take :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;‘One with the open eyes and one with closed’,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the latter was cheaper so, I did that and read and thought a lot. The beautiful thing about this process is that it starts with identification of difference between Being Lonely and Being Alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds odd?? Bear with me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Being Lonely’ is not a choice, it’s not a happy space for your mind to be, you don’t choose it; by the virtue of circumstances it has been forced upon you. ‘Being Alone’ however, is completely different and therapeutic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2017, I moved to a different country and started talking to people from different age-groups, countries, cultural beliefs, socio-economic status, etc. At first idea of meeting new people, knowing different culture, does sound interesting and I don’t deny that it was great fun. Having said that, on careful observation though, you tend to find some similarities. Some obvious, some not-so-obvious.What am I talking about? What is it that I found?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok! So, I found out that root cause of most of people’s problems was consequentially because of Being lonely’(either at that time or some time in the past) rather than Being alone. Take a second here and do an honest evaluation that which of the above two categories you could associate most with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s address the elephant in the room properly now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loneliness Is As Bad For Your Health As Smoking 15 Cigarettes A Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of it in this way, if a person is lonely certainly at some point some sort of desperation will crawl in. Now, a desperate person is not in a position to choose but rather more willing to compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the above in mind, now consider the resource intensive environment we have been nurtured in, this very word Compromise has a negative connotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lore of ‘Follow your passion’ is fed &amp;amp; injected into our brains since childhood, which would not have been so bad if only acceptance was taught along. So with this frame of mind, problems like these are inevitable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Been/Being in a physically or mentally abusive relationship&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doubts about marriage&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seeking approval/reassurance/validation from relationships or peers&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alcohol (Hey! you hiding in the veil of social drinking… you sure?), drugs, porn - addiction&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finding a balance between personal goals and family responsibility&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doing a good job, good salary, good city still not content&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have amazing friends to hangout with but none could be relied upon&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doing 100 things throughout the day, just so to not feel hollow and empty&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Staying in bed, trying to sleep but end up thinking 1000 useless thoughts&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get the picture!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait Wait! The problem doesn’t end there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As opportunistic as the world is today for a competent individual, it enforces a collective ideology of doing things fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Want to open start-up? Hurry up and take the first mover’s advantage”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Want to become best in a field, put-in 10000 hours of work as quickly as you can”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Like that guy/girl just quickly go and ask her out”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re not married yet? Hurry up! the clock is ticking”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End result, you end up being a person who thinks fast, not giving one’s brain enough time to evaluate and reflect. The most common consequence, you speak and do things that assure fruits-of-regret/guilt. Don’t have deeper and quality relationships in your life? You are stuck to something from past? Unsure about everything you wish to do? Humans dominate this planet because we thought faster than other species but:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;“There is more to life than increasing its speed.” -Mahatma Gandhi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sorry if I am being the first person to throw light on something like this. A person driven by compromise and programmed to think fast is more likely to take impulsive not-so-smart decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are, as I mentioned earlier, just symptoms hinting to a potentially bigger emotional turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rightly said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;“All of humanity’s problems stem from man’s inability to sit quietly in a room alone.” ― Blaise Pascal, Pensées
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you sat quietly, without music or distraction and just experienced ‘being’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objectivity, will-power calibration are just some of the advantages of doing that but let’s keep that for some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, what’s important is that if you haven’t done that there are good chances that you might be going through an emotional crisis. Something needs to be done about it. If you’re not facing any such issues, then great, skip to the last para straight away!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a need of developing a coping mechanism. To begin with, take the easiest step find a friend, a family member or a professional if need be. Sit and for once, talk. It might not change anything or solve anything but will give you enough assurance to proceed and identify steps to deal with it. Based on my small experience, I can almost assure you that many around you face the same issue, some better at hiding than the other. Open-up and you’ll see!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, don’t be afraid of feeling stupid or a fool. It’s only human to feel vulnerable and in fact quite mature to accept that. It also gives other person an opportunity to be honest and as it follows mutual vulnerability fosters closeness, you might strengthen your relationship with the person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have any of these issues (and you’ve skipped the above paragraphs and jumped right on to here), then, first, go ahead and say thank you to your friends/family/partner, basically your support system. Once you’ve done that, please go and talk to people around you and give them an opportunity to speak, they might not have anyone to talk to or might be too hesitant to say personal stuff.You don’t have to judge them, you don’t necessarily need to even provide a solution, good-old listening works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For once, make an effort to be the person you probably needed once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post wasn’t to educate or lecture you but rather just strike a chord of awareness. Probably, about something that you already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stitch in time, saves nine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S: If you wish to reach out to me for your views on this piece, suggestions, critique…anything. Find and message me on Twitter @InDevOut.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
